<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CSE 390 A1: Android Programming</title>
    <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/</link>
    <description>Recent content on CSE 390 A1: Android Programming</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 16:05:07 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework 3</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 16:05:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-3/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the branch &lt;code&gt;failing-tests-1&lt;/code&gt; from the mdr-original project you built
for Homework 1. Many tests should fail. Fix both the tests in the &lt;code&gt;android&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;androidTests&lt;/code&gt; configurations. Some rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DO NOT CHANGE THE TESTS&lt;/strong&gt;: You should not have to edit any test code to
get these to pass. All changes should be made in non-test Java files and in
xml files. If you think you found a reason you need to change test code, and
you REALLY REALLY REALLY think you&amp;rsquo;re right, email me and ask.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DO NOT LOOK AT THE DIFF&lt;/strong&gt;: This is a git repo. The nature of version
control allows you to fix all the tests via nothing more than git trickery.
This would be super lame, however. Android is something where you learn by
doing. If you cheat, you&amp;rsquo;re only hurting yourself. Further, these
assignments are largely optional. You could just not do it and save the
effort you think you&amp;rsquo;re saving by using the diff. If you&amp;rsquo;re taking the time
to revert the diff and find yourself feeling clever, that feeling might be
misplaced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;backstory&#34;&gt;Backstory&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An incompetent collaborator has gotten ahold of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/srsudar/mdr-original&#34;&gt;mdr-original&lt;/a&gt; project. Thinking
themselves brilliant, they&amp;rsquo;ve made loads of edits but never run the tests. &amp;lsquo;I
am god&amp;rsquo;s gift to Android programming&amp;rsquo;, you imagine them saying as they type
&lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being the selfless hero that you are, it falls to you to save the project from
incompetence. You clench your jaw, imagine yourself on a mountain before a flag
waving triumphantly in the wind, and with a steely gaze you get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-how&#34;&gt;The &amp;lsquo;How&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The broken tests are on the branch called &lt;code&gt;failing-tests-1&lt;/code&gt;. Assuming you are
using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; from the command line, you would run this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;git fetch
git checkout failing-tests-1
git branch # should output &#39;*failing-tests-1&#39; or similar
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the code in Android Studio. You should encounter a build error complaining
about a tool not found (unless you&amp;rsquo;d installed it previously).  This was
intentional. &amp;gt;:) In the real world you&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix a lot of these types of
errors. Better to get comfortable with them when there&amp;rsquo;s someone you can ask
(me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of tests in Android Studio: &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;androidTest&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt; are unit tests that can run on the JVM. In this case we&amp;rsquo;ve configured
them to use Robolectric (more on this next week). &lt;code&gt;androidTest&lt;/code&gt; are tests that
need to run on an actual device. To run these you&amp;rsquo;ll need either a physical
device or an emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right click on the &lt;code&gt;android&lt;/code&gt; tests and click &amp;lsquo;Run Tests&amp;rsquo;. &lt;strong&gt;29 tests should
fail&lt;/strong&gt;. Your job is to get them passing. Fixing one bug might fix more than one
tests, so it&amp;rsquo;s not as bad as it may seem at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right click on the &lt;code&gt;androidTest&lt;/code&gt; tests and click &amp;lsquo;Run Tests&amp;rsquo;. &lt;strong&gt;1 test should
fail&lt;/strong&gt;. You need an emulator or physical device for this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the logs for the errors. This will be helpful in many cases, and will
tell you were to look. Most of these tests have to do with Android UI (e.g.
&lt;code&gt;View&lt;/code&gt;s), and one or two may pertain to the lifecycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should &lt;strong&gt;not need to edit the tests for any of these to pass&lt;/strong&gt;. If you
think you do, email me and I will tell you if I&amp;rsquo;ve made a mistake. I&amp;rsquo;ll forward
your email to the list, giving you credit. Tears of joy will be shed, glory
will be basked in. Life will be good. (But seriously, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you&amp;rsquo;ll need
to edit any tests.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should also &lt;strong&gt;not look at the diff&lt;/strong&gt;. I could have done this in a way that
didn&amp;rsquo;t give you access to the git history. I didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was worth the
effort. If you&amp;rsquo;re cheating, you&amp;rsquo;re only hurting yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the tl;dr section for more on the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that UIs are generally specified two places:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An xml file, e.g. &lt;code&gt;res/layout/activity_main.xml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Java Activity, e.g. &lt;code&gt;org/mamasdelrio/android/MainActivity.java&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll have to edit more than these files, but those are good places to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get stuck, &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalyst.uw.edu/gopost/conversation/sudars/974700&#34;&gt;ask questions on this thread on the message
board&lt;/a&gt;. If that
doesn&amp;rsquo;t work or you don&amp;rsquo;t feel comfortable posting there, I&amp;rsquo;m also happy to
field emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-why&#34;&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Why&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tests try to give you more exposure to UI, &lt;code&gt;View&lt;/code&gt;s, and &lt;code&gt;Activity&lt;/code&gt;s. Next
week you&amp;rsquo;ll have to create UIs (with tests!) from scratch yourself. Use this to
get accustomed to how everything works together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;submitting&#34;&gt;Submitting&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fork the repo on github and submit your changes to a &lt;code&gt;failing-tests-1&lt;/code&gt; branch
there. &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/fork-a-repo/&#34;&gt;Here is a guide on github
forking&lt;/a&gt;. Email me the link with
&amp;lsquo;HW 3: Submission&amp;rsquo; in the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize this is a bit of a git-heavy and github-heavy class if you&amp;rsquo;re not
familiar with these tools. If you find this overwhelming, email me and I will
try to help you understand them. These are things that you&amp;rsquo;ll be better off
knowing, and I am consciously trying to encourage that you become comfortable
with them. If you &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t want to use github, you can email me a patch
file with the same subject as above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 3</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 16:03:20 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-3/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;recap-and-slides&#34;&gt;Recap and Slides&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we talked about Building a UI. Slides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Bz13hejFW1ylJgI_bnvmof7oaOcTVWFn6pLQgyLIeL0/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;Lecture 3: Building a
UI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people were gone for the career fair. Email me or come to office hours
if anything is confusing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework 2</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 08:34:52 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Homework 2 is to choose an open source Android project and build it locally.
I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalyst.uw.edu/gopost/board/sudars/43331/&#34;&gt;started a discussion
board&lt;/a&gt; for the course and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://catalyst.uw.edu/gopost/conversation/sudars/973883&#34;&gt;started a thread&lt;/a&gt;
where I&amp;rsquo;d like people to post the projects that they choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homework 2 (assigned on 2016-10-11) is to find an open source Android Project,
build it locally, and run it on your device/emulator. Some will be easier than
others. Some may be really hard. &lt;strong&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;ve chosen and built a project, post
it on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://catalyst.uw.edu/gopost/conversation/sudars/973883&#34;&gt;Homework 2
thread&lt;/a&gt; on the
message board.&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m curious to see what you choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Only choose a project someone else has posted if you have already tried a
different project but haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to get it working.&lt;/strong&gt; If you&amp;rsquo;re
re-posting a project, include the previous project that you tried and the error
that kept you from building it. I basically just don&amp;rsquo;t want the first person
that posts a simple-to-build project to ruin the experience for someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the real world if you&amp;rsquo;re working on an Android project, odds are you&amp;rsquo;ll
first have to build someone else&amp;rsquo;s existing code. It&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to get
familiar with it. If you&amp;rsquo;re choosing a project from github, check out the
README for a &amp;ldquo;Building&amp;rdquo; section or something similar, as projects will
frequently include pointers on vagaries of the build.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 2: The Lifecycle</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 08:23:37 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;recap-and-slides&#34;&gt;Recap and Slides&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we talked about the Android lifecycle. Here is a link to the slides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1bKBzo0rbi8NsmZc15VpX6DXrIJ4zPMX71EBpYIR2k2o/edit#slide=id.g183ccd2a56_0_5&#34;&gt;Lecture 2: Android Lifecycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created a repo called &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/srsudar/cse390-android-playground&#34;&gt;cse390-android-playground&lt;/a&gt;
that I&amp;rsquo;ll keep updating over the course of the quarter to demonstrate small,
bite-sized pieces of code outside of a coherent app context. As the README
there indicates, it is organized by branches. This week check out
&lt;code&gt;intent-basics&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;lifecycle-logs&lt;/code&gt; and mess around with the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some more links you might find useful. Some of the images on the
slides came from these pages, and they provide a lot more detail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/guide/components/activities.html&#34;&gt;Activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/training/basics/activity-lifecycle/index.html&#34;&gt;Activity Lifecycle
Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/training/basics/activity-lifecycle/starting.html&#34;&gt;Starting an
Activity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Office Hours Mondays 4-5</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/office-hours/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 12:42:18 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/office-hours/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Based on the Doodle poll, office hours will be &lt;strong&gt;Mondays, 4-5&lt;/strong&gt;. All the rooms
are booked, so for now we&amp;rsquo;ll just meet in &lt;strong&gt;CSE 214&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the office hours were formerly in the third floor breakout, but the
location has moved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Room Change: GUG 218</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/room-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 08:27:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/room-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To try and better accommodate overloads, we have moved rooms to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washington.edu/maps/#!/gug&#34;&gt;Guggenheim
218&lt;/a&gt;. It has windows and lacks a giant
pillar in the middle of the room, so that is a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My inbox has been relatively quiet, given how finicky Android Studio can be. If
you get stuck, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homework 1</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 17:31:19 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/homework/homework-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Your homework for this week is to get your dev environment set up. Once it is
running, create a new app like I demonstrated in the slides (Lecture 1, see
previous post) and run it on either your device or an emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, download and open this project in Android Studio:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/srsudar/mdr-original&#34;&gt;https://github.com/srsudar/mdr-original&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run the tests and run the app on your device or emulator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you get stuck email me and I will help you!!!&lt;/strong&gt; There is nothing worse
than being stuck on something like configuration or not being able to run code
that other people can run. If any of this is confusing (i.e. how do I download
and open a project?), email me and I will explain it better!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away with the &lt;code&gt;mdr-original&lt;/code&gt; project someone got an error saying that
android-22 was not found on their machine. This means the SDK for Android
version 22 is not installed, and many of you will likely see the same error.
This is not an error with the app but with your build environment, and is one
of the most common types of Android errors. Launch the SDK manager (as shown in
the slides), and install version 22. It should then work (or at least that
error should go away).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Week 1 Intro</title>
      <link>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-1-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 16:54:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://courses.cs.washington.edu/courses/cse390a1/16au/post/week-1-intro/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Makeshift office hours this week on &lt;strong&gt;Wednesday, Oct 5, 1030-1130 in CSE
678&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone asked me after class if you should be able to build your own Android
App by the time the course is over. That should have been on my &amp;ldquo;goals of the
course slide&amp;rdquo;, as heck yes it is a goal. In fact, after Homework 1 you&amp;rsquo;ll have
already built your own app. It is crummy and boring, but built it you have. By
the time the course is over, hopefully you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to build your own app
that isn&amp;rsquo;t crummy or boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a weird course because it is about a specific technology. The only way
you can really learn a technology is by using it. Writing code, running code,
encountering bugs that are confusing and beyond your control, being alternately
jubilant and miserable&amp;ndash;all these things are part of learning something like
Android. Unfortunately, for a once a week credit/no-credit class, we don&amp;rsquo;t have
a lab component and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to require a bunch of assignments, so I&amp;rsquo;m just
going to be standing in front of you talking. &lt;strong&gt;But you will only really learn
Android if you do the assignments and mess around with the code.&lt;/strong&gt; For that
reason I suggest you spend as much time as you can on the assignments until you
complete them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;office-hours&#34;&gt;Office Hours&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please use &lt;a href=&#34;http://doodle.com/poll/2ap5tvbrekccm99n&#34;&gt;the Doodle poll&lt;/a&gt; to pick a
time that works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we&amp;rsquo;re waiting for the final Doodle results to filter in, I&amp;rsquo;m going to have a
temporary office hours this week before we settle on a regular time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s office hours is &lt;strong&gt;Oct 5, 1030-1130am in CSE 678&lt;/strong&gt;. This works
for most people according to the poll. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for you, vote in the
Doodle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to bring your machines to have me help install Android Studio from
scratch or to have me help troubleshoot errors you&amp;rsquo;ve encountered doing
Homework 1. If you want to come and start Homework 1 with me sitting there,
just in case you encounter an error, that is fine by me too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;slides&#34;&gt;Slides&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the lecture slides from this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1G6xdqkHpiOpb3667t3-fK9b_tRFS7z644RYGjYMDhE0/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;Lecture 0:
Administrivia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1cTJ2wW5DHLl262TRqjKKlSLEsgW3gQECrQVF9gHvCf0/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;Lecture 1: Android Dev 101 &amp;amp; App
Anatomy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;about-the-site&#34;&gt;About the Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made this site using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tanksuzuki&#34;&gt;Asuka Suzuki&lt;/a&gt; for his MIT-licensed
&lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/hemingway/&#34;&gt;Hemingway
theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>